<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The death of God's Moses's [sic] considered being the substance of a sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. Francis Johnson, minister of the gospel, sometimes fellow of All-Souls, and afterwards Master of University Colledge in Oxford, who died in London, October the 9th. 1677 / by J. Ll.</title>
            <author>J. Ll.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2617A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24021266</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24021266</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1705:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The death of God's Moses's [sic] considered being the substance of a sermon preached at the funeral of Mr. Francis Johnson, minister of the gospel, sometimes fellow of All-Souls, and afterwards Master of University Colledge in Oxford, who died in London, October the 9th. 1677 / by J. Ll.</title>
                  <author>J. Ll.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for, and are to be sold by Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 19.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Johnson, Francis, d. 1677.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Joshua I, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DEATH OF Gods Moſes's CONSIDERED: Being the ſubſtance of a SERMON Preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Francis Johnſon,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſometimes Fellow of <hi>All-ſouls,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Maſter of <hi>Univerſity Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Who died in <hi>London, October</hi> the 9th. 1677.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. Ll.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He being dead, yet ſpeaketh,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for, and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three-Crowns</hi> over againſt the Great Conduit at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109618:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109618:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Sermon when Preached was not in the leaſt deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thy view, but by a true friend of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Perſon, much against my inclination, is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced out of my hands into the Preſs. The trite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Apology will (likely enough) make it leſs believed: but ſure I am, whereſover, how often ſoever it hath been falſe here it is very true. If I deſerve not thy belief and ſo I am denied it, I cannot help it. Though the diſcourſe doth not, aſſuredly the ſubject and the worthy Miniſter deceaſed abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly deſerves to be known and publiſhed. In it thou wilt find ſomewhat more, and poſſibly ſomewhat leſs than was Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Som will judge here is too much, and ſome it may be too little: Cenſure as thou pleaſeſt, or rather as thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est. Labour (with me) to imitate his vertues who is gone, and if this Sermon ſhall prove instrumental to the reformation and preparing of any for the ſerious hour of death, I ſhall be very thankful, and I pray God it may. I earneſtly beg young Miniſters their favourable interpretation, as well as
<pb facs="tcp:109618:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſcientious conſideration of the laſt uſe. I preſume onely humbly to adviſe my Juniors, nor them neither as though I thought not ſome, ſo as to years, much my Seniors other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Nor is my advice intended for any, more or further, than it is for my ſelf: if none elſe have any need of it, I am glad of it, and hope they will pardon me that I have uſed the Plural, if I ought to have uſed the Singular Number. What any full fraught with humor, that yet want ability to be Criticks, who have more Brow than Brain, and more Forehead than Head, more Supercilious Confidence than Modeſty and Underſtanding, ſhall ſay or think of it, I am not at all ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109618:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DEATH OF GOD'S MOSES'S CONSIDERED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Joſhua 1.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Moſes my Servant is dead.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>YOu may poſſibly wonder why I choſe ſuch a Text concerning ſo great and ſo publick a perſon as <hi>Moſes</hi> was, to ſpeak of, and from him whoſe death is the ſad occaſion of our coming here this day: but when you know and remember how great and publick a perſon he alſo hath been in former days, though of late years buried in obſcurity; and of what Magnitude this Star that is fallen, was, who in his laſt Winter ſtormy nights of trouble and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was indeed inveloped in the clouds as if quite ſet, and for ever diſappeared, yet in fairer times gave as great a light in his leſſer Sphere, and ſhone as much in his more confined Orb, as did <hi>Moſes</hi> in his greater. When you have thought of this, you will need no Rhetorick to perſwade you to abate your marvel; but readily think the Text enough adapted to the Providence: and ſure it cannot be much amiſs to ground his Euneral Sermon, who (as if repute and eſtimation were ſome great afflictions, and to be likely to be valued according to his deſerts, were to be in danger) ſtudiouſly concealed himſelf and his great worth from being known and honour'd, to ground it (I ſay) upon him, who was hid in an ark of Bulruſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſhua,</hi> to whom God here ſpeaks, is ſuppoſed to have writ, as this Book, which goes under his name, ſo the later end of the former from the mention of the death of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109618:4"/>
            <p>When God ſpoke theſe words to <hi>Joſhua,</hi> whether when the thirty days of mourning for <hi>Moſes</hi> were expired as ſome think: or whether after the elapſing of a longer time (as ſeems probable from the laſt clauſe of the 6. <hi>v.</hi> of the 34. of <hi>Deut.</hi>) is uncertain.</p>
            <p>The words are the great God's little and ſhort (yet full and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive) account of the great man <hi>Moſes:</hi> and in them we have two parts:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. His Life, <hi>My ſervant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. His Death, <hi>is dead.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>He wore out, and beſtowed all his life in the Service of his God, and ſo died. His obedience was not interrupted by any chaſin of idleneſs or apoſtacy: but as he lived Gods ſervant, he took care to die ſo: He would not die without living, nor live without dying his.</p>
            <p>As to his name <hi>(Moſes)</hi> called by the <hi>Egyptians Hermes,</hi> by <hi>Mane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho Oſarſeph,</hi> by the <hi>Grecians</hi> with a ſmall alteration of the Hebrew (as ſome think) <hi>Muſeus:</hi> Whether he was firſt named by <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being an Egyptian, in that language <hi>Monies</hi> which ſignifies the ſame with <hi>Moſes:</hi> whether it be derived from <hi>Mo,</hi> water and <hi>Hyſe</hi> Kept, or (as ſeems moſt likely) from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he drew, becauſe he was <hi>drawn</hi> from the water ſide, with a prophetick intimation, how he ſhould <hi>draw</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and how much he ſhould rule the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Water in their behalf, and draw them through it, as he was drawn from it: (Which name or at leaſt the thing ſignified by it, <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſeems to allude to in that verſe which is upon a good reaſon underſtood of him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) or whether <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daughter being inſtructed by <hi>Moſes</hi> his mother and ſiſter that he was an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> learnt this name from them, and ſo gave it him. Whether he had any other name given him before upon his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and whether that was <hi>Joachim</hi> as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> thinks, (poſſibly from <hi>Numerius</hi> the Philoſopher) who ſays he was ſo called: or whether he was called <hi>Melchi,</hi> that is, my King, after his reception into heaven, as the ſame <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> fancies; and many ſuch like queſtions of him, are uncertain, not worth our while to diſpute: but this is certain that a great man he was, ſo great that ſome of the Jewiſh Rabbies, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.7. That when he died <hi>his eyes were not dim, nor his natural force abated,</hi> ſay, that therefore he was an Angel and did not properly die: and others of them, that with his rod he wan'd off the Angel of death: inſomuch that had not God himſelf taken away his ſoul with a kiſs, he could not have died: So great was he in the Jews eſteem, that they would not look upon him as man, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109618:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore was he privately buried, and for ever hid that they might not worſhip him as God, as ſome conjecture, who from the Apocryphal writings conclude, that was the cauſe of the diſpute between <hi>Michael</hi> and the Divel about the body of <hi>Moſes, Jude v.</hi> 9. and it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable. A ſervant of God he was, and a very great and eminent one, and yet die he muſt, and though he was ſo great, and there was no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in <hi>Iſrael</hi> like to him; yet, <hi>He that is the leaſt</hi> (Miniſter) <hi>in the Kingdom of God,</hi> in Goſpel times, is upon ſome account <hi>greater then he:</hi> and yet (as we ſee) they die too. Which brings me to the <hi>Obſervation,</hi> which not only with reſpect to him upon whoſe account we are here, but ſeverall other Miniſters who very lately have dropped one after another, almoſt all together, is much to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Gods Servants, even his</hi> Moſes's <hi>die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to the Doctrine, I ſhall ſhew,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What Gods ſervants are or how men come to be ſo.</item>
               <item>2. Further explain the Text, by deſcribing <hi>Moſes</hi> and proving him Gods ſervant by,
<list>
                     <item>1. Some of his actions.</item>
                     <item>2. Some of the Characters the Scriptures give of him, and ſpeak to both theſe as far as they will freely go with us without force compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with regard to death, and the Reverend Miniſter we are now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. Shew you the Reaſons why God's <hi>Moſes's</hi> die, (laſtly) make Application.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What God's ſervants are, or how men come to be ſo? and to this purpoſe two things are neceſſary.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A ſolemn ſerious chooſing and taking God for their Maſter, and reſigning up themſelves to him, to be his thorough faithful ſervants. Thoſe who would <hi>be avouched by God, to be his peculiar people,</hi> Deut. 26.18. and enjoy the performance of <hi>his promiſe,</hi> muſt ſolemnly <hi>avouch him to be their God, to walk in his ways, and to keep his Statutes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> Deut. 26.17. Though they may not mercenarily capitulate with him for his reward, yet they may and muſt ſeriouſly indent with him for their ſervice, cheerfully undertake it, and faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe by his aſſiſtance to do thoſe works he is pleaſed to allot them. Every little reſentment of Religion, every faint wiſh, or ſmall velleities for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs will not ſerve the turn in ſo great a matter; nor yet will every real purpoſe, every true reſolution, nor every hearty promiſe, nor any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109618:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of them, nor all of them, wreſted by ſome black and threatning provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or ſome very awakening importunate Sermon that will not be denied, if only light, tranſient, and accidental, and not brought into the ſolemnity of ſome ſuch thing as a day of Faſt and Humiliation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately and unreſervedly to reſign up all to God. Baptiſm, which is our ſolemn entrance into the Church of God, requires our ſerious and ſolemn owning of it, and will not be put off with a ſmall touch by the word, and now and then ſome good motions of the Spirit of God, that (it may be) produce a few ſighs and tears, and then vaniſh, and we hear no more of them. That there are ſo many rotten profeſſors, ſo many half Chriſtians, ſo many wavering and ſcandalous Church-members, ſo many vain Religioniſts, and ſo many diſorderly and looſe pretenders to holineſs: ſuch multitudes that deſpond, unbelieve and deſpair, and ſo great a plenty of backſliders and apoſtates; may (I conceive) be very reaſonably imputed to the general neglect of imbarking into ſerious Chriſtianity, by private as well as publick days of Faſting and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Some ſuch thing our Saviour ſeems to intimate when he advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us <hi>to ſit down and conſider, Luk.</hi> 14.28, 29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to commence Chriſtians. It is no wonder that they ſtumble and fall, and miſs to reach the end of their Chriſtian race, that ſet not out fairly and conſiderately. It is not probable that a few faint diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and well-meaning but volatile inclinations to vertue, will ever carry a man to heaven, unleſs fixt and brought to a conſiſtency by a deliberate covenanting with God. Miſtake not thy ſelf, man, eternal happineſs will never be thy portion, for all thy <hi>good wiſhes and good meanings, the good will and good heart,</hi> thou ſayeſt thou haſt; without ſolemn and remorſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reflections upon the paſt part of thy life, with careful, ſtudied and ſincere reſolutions againſt all thy ſins for the time to come: nor will theſe avail, though never ſo hearty and ſtated, unleſs thy ſubſequent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours correſpond and be conſiſtent with them: which leads in the next thing that makes men God's <hi>Servants,</hi> and how they come to be ſo, which is</item>
               <item>2. A careful and conſcientious practice according to their choice of God for their Lord and Maſter; doing the work he conſigns them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their promiſes to, and keeping their Covenants with him. That man is no ſervant that <hi>ſays he will do his Maſters Will and doth it not;</hi> how fairly ſoever he might promiſe, if he ſpends his time in idleneſs, or in doing his own, and not his Maſters pleaſure. Such are thoſe men, who yet will needs uſurp the name of Chriſtians, that are very liberal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109618:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their Vows, Promiſes, and Covenants with Almighty God, but as prodigal of their violations of them, that break as ſoon as they make them, that will do what Chriſt will have them, ſo he will be bound to command them nothing, but what they will have him; and willingly obey his Will, ſo it be not againſt their own: but this is not to be his Servants, but their own Maſters; and they that are ſo, ſhall be their own rewarders too. If we pick and chooſe out of the Commands of God what likes us beſt, what ſuits our humors, or our tempers, our Callings, or our Opinions, and neglect the reſt; we violate our Covenants, and muſt not expect to be treated as his Servants, but as his enemies. How often doth he complain of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Covenant-Breaking, and how ſeverely doth he puniſh them for it? nor are we like to eſcape his ſtroaks, be our Profeſſions, be our Promiſes, be our Prayers, be our Pretences never ſo high; <hi>If we live after the Fleſh, we ſhall dye,</hi> Rom. 8. Let us therefore labour after both theſe qualifications: let us ſeriouſly bind our ſelves to God, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerve all our time with him. Such a Servant of God was <hi>Moſes;</hi> who was dedicated to him, and made good his Dedication in the whole courſe of his life, may we be ſuch too, ſo ſhall we have (as <hi>Moſes</hi> had) his good teſtimony of us in another World, which is infinitely better than living in this. God's <hi>Enter thou faithful Servant into the joy of thy Maſter,</hi> is far more comfortable, than the Sinners, <hi>Eat, Drink, and be Merry;</hi> his good Word will paſs for us through all eternity. Thrice happy is that Man, whom God ſtiles <hi>his Servant,</hi> when he is dead. Men and Angels may be too charitable, and give too favourable judgments of us; they that ſee not the heart, may think and ſay it is very good: Alas! many are here Canonized for Saints, that in the other World are damned amongſt the Devils; and laviſhly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for eminent Chriſtians, who are condemned by God for Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Wretches. Men praiſe they know not what, they know not who, they know not why: but Gods Elegies tell no lyes, nor do his <hi>Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums</hi> flatter or diſſemble. He is a good Man indeed whoſe <hi>Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> is made by God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But <hi>Moſes</hi> was not only a Servant of God, but he was ſo in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Station, he had the care of the Houſe of God, and ſo he was Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical of the ſucceeding Miniſters of the Goſpel, which is one of our proper concerns to conſider at this time; and therefore from the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice God takes of the Death of <hi>Moſes,</hi> we alſo have taken notice of the death of his Succeſſors, and have obſerved that his <hi>Moſeses</hi> dye. But,</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109618:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">2. Further to explain the Text, and the Doctrine, I ſhall deſcribe <hi>Moſes,</hi> and prove to you that he was God's Servant, and I do both theſe,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By ſome of his actions, particularly as,
<list>
                     <item>1. The Series of Miracles which by the Authority and Command of God, he wrought in Oppoſition to the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and in Defence of the <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 4.16. to whom as well as to <hi>Aaron</hi> he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of God; he had the command of Heaven, and the Water, and Earth, and the Meteors of the Air, and therein as well as in other things was a clear Type of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>The Wind and the Sea obeyed him;</hi> and ſeemed to have ſucceeded or rather exceeded <hi>Adam</hi> in his Original Power: The Animals come at his Call to infeſt the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> march in Battalia to <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Court, conquer and force him to yield and ſurrender: without any more words, upon the Kings refuſal he ſends an army of Senſitives to ſubdue him (as he after victualed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with a regiment of Quails, and a ſhower of Manna, <hi>Exo.</hi> 16.) He had the diſpoſal of the King of Terrors, killed and ſaved alive whom and what he pleaſed: and yet even he, maugre this ſtrange authority he had over, muſt be ſubject to the Empire, and feel the ſtroke of death. <hi>This great Moſes alſo died.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. He conquered <hi>Amalek</hi> for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and yet himſelf uſed no weapon, nor no hoſtility, <hi>Ex.</hi> 11. &amp; 13. when the lifting up of his hands did more injure the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and more befriend the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> than the lifting up of <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s and his armies, and there was as much fear of the falling of <hi>Moſes</hi> his hand as there was of the hoſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his hands were ſteady, therefore <hi>Joſhua diſcomfited Amalek and his people,</hi> 12, 13, <hi>v.</hi> yet for all this great ſervice he did God and his Church, he was not exempted from mortality: this ſo triumphant conqueror, and ſo ſelect a <hi>Servant of God is dead.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. He faſted fourty days and fourty nights: and ſo typified our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, <hi>whoſe meat and drink</hi> was to receive and <hi>do his Fathers will:</hi> and one would think, having lived ſo long, notwithſtanding the decaya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of nature without continued ſuſtenance, he would prove for ever after (as ſome Jewiſh Rabbies fancy he did) death-proof and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal; but no, it was <hi>appointed</hi> alſo for him <hi>to dye.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. He wrote by the inſpiration of God the beginning, the firſt five Books of the holy Scriptures: <hi>if they hear not Moſes,</hi> Luk. 16.31. ſays our Saviour: and the Apoſtle <hi>when Moſes is read,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. that is that part of the Scripture which was written by him. One of the Fathers ſeems to underſtand by the <hi>five words</hi> of the Apoſtle in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:109618:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>14.19. the five Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as if he were preferring the preaching, the neceſſary injunctions of the law before the miraculous gift of tongues. <hi>Moſes</hi> (ſome think) was born <hi>A. M.</hi> 2373. and wrote be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Homer</hi> the firſt Grecian writer 540 years, before <hi>Sanconiathan</hi> the firſt <hi>Phenician</hi> writer 200 years: though in <hi>Phenicia</hi> ſome (I ſuppoſe falſly) conjecture letters were firſt found out. He was the firſt man the Holy Ghoſt ever inſpired in writing: yet and though he ever lives in thoſe writings he muſt die.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. The ſecond way I propoſed to deſcribe <hi>Moſes</hi> and prove him the ſervant of God, was by the Characters the Scriptures give of him: and we find in the Word of God that,
<list>
                     <item>1. He was a man of prayer, an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed, that always conquered men and prevailed with God, had even what he would of him: and in ſome ſenſe reverſed the decrees of Heaven: <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.10, 11, 14. So powerful was he in prayer, that when God abſolutely and perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily deſigns the ruine of a people, he makes it appear by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that <hi>Moſes, Jer.</hi> 15.1. if he were praying for them, ſhould not be able to retrieve them, <hi>q. d.</hi> he who once did ſtrangely pray my mind toward this people ſhould now fail to do it. And what a ſtrange ſpirit of prayer had this ſecond <hi>Moſes</hi> whoſe departure from us hath brought us here this day! what an unheard of fluency of tears, word and matter would he altogether pour upon his hearers! how would the Rhetorick of his boyling affections and moſt ſerious earneſtneſs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb and yet greatly recommend the oratory of his words! have you not ſeen <hi>rivers of tears running down his eyes,</hi> when he hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing and praying for you? with what brokenneſs of ſpirit, with what ſelf-abhorrency, and with what deep reverence would he ſpeak to God?</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Moſes</hi> was a man of learning, which he imployed for God: <hi>Acts</hi> 22. he was verſed in all the wiſdom of the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> which (it is likely)was then couched in Hieroglyphicks, if (as ſome think) they had not then the uſe of letters which were not then invented, or at leaſt, they had them not: though its poſſible they might have had them from the <hi>Phenicians,</hi> as they from <hi>Abraham.</hi> So was our <hi>Moſes,</hi> though he made no pompous ſhew of it. Amongſt other of his excellencies in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he was well read in controverſies, particularly he was an able de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Truth againſt the growing and ſo much improved errors of <hi>Arminianiſm:</hi> and his learning was the more lovely and valuable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe richly enameled with modeſty, for as,</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Moſes</hi> was a modeſt man, who could by no means be perſwaded to think himſelf fit for ſo worthy an employment as God deſigned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109618:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>him; <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.10, 13. ſo was our <hi>Moſes,</hi> his thoughts of himſelf were as little, and as low as were his accompliſhments great and high: He was ſo far from blurting out his knowledge in all companies, or waiting his opportunity to be guilty of oſtentation (as ſome do) that with too great care he hid his eminent parts from the view of all, and (juſt like <hi>Moſes</hi>) as his modeſty was (if there was any unequalneſs in his graces) one of his moſt reſplendent vertues: So the exceſs of it was his moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent infirmity. How hardly was he drawn, and how difficultly tolled into that wortk which he was prompted too by his free and religious education, and wherein he did far ſurpaſs and excel moſt of the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Preachers, and what could be the reaſon of this his very injurious unwillingneſs to be publick? what, but a too modeſt ſenſe, (I ſpeak what I know) I ſay a too modeſt ſenſe of that unfitneſs, which from him was always at remoteſt diſtance. But to haſten, we find in Scripture that,</item>
                     <item>4. Laſtly, <hi>Moſes</hi> was a <hi>very meek and patient man above all the men which were upon the face of the earth:</hi> amongſt the many cloſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind provocations of a ſtubborn and refractory people, and very uncivil affronts that were put upon him by the obſtinate children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we find him but once guilty of any thing like a paſſionate word, and that was when they did abundantly deſerve it, at leaſt upon Gods account: and ſure it could not be a ſinful (though it were an angry) expreſſion, to call them <hi>Rebels, Num.</hi> 20.2, 3, 4, 5, &amp; 10. <hi>v.</hi> who were ſo indeed: and ſo plainly and notoriouſly rebelled againſt their God, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pined and murmured not againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> only, but againſt him too, and againſt him moſt: and therefore though I know ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators think this one of <hi>Moſes</hi> his faults for which he was excluded <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet (with ſubmiſſion) I cannot think ſo. So patient was <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> thus was the Original, and juſt like him was our Copy. Fancy a man the beſt of meer men, who formerly was followed with continual affluences of the things of this world, through the whirl of Providence, brought to a condition next to poor and indigent: that was the deſired company of the greater and more refined ſort, forced to converſe with the poorer and more ordinary: and who governed the higheſt rank of men in their advances in the ſuperior liberal Arts and Sciences, and chiefeſt Profeſſions, compelled (more indeed to divert a greater noiſe than by want and neceſſity) to ſit amidſt the cries and clamors of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and inſtruct them in the Rudiments of Reading: and in a word (not to enumerate, for it would be much too tedious and too ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) fancy one once encompaſſed with all the afflictions of <hi>Job,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109618:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>amongſt the reſt that worſt than all, <hi>the dins of a fooliſh woman:</hi> perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endued with <hi>Jobs</hi> patience too, that bears all with as great an unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſs of mind as if in the higheſt Apex of proſperity: and then will you but begin to think equally of his patience. In ſhort, none but <hi>Moſes, Job,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> would bear what he did. And thus I have done with the deſcription of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of his ſecond. We now come to ſhew you,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. The Reaſons why Gods <hi>Moſeses,</hi> his Miniſters die, and they are theſe,
<list>
                     <item>1. They have the ſame cauſes of death with others. Theſe ſpiritual men have bodies that contain humors fermentable into diſtempers as well as others: and dwell in houſes of clay, that are tottering and decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as others do. They are not ſecured by their ſtudies, nor by their employment, nor by their piety from the miſeries of humane nature, but rather the more expoſed to them (as I ſhall ſhew you under the next head). Theſe Angels of Churches aſſume, lodge in and inform material vehicles compounded of diviſible parts and eaſie ſeparable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, that lie open to the wind and weather, ſickneſſes, pains and caſualities, and often need repair and Phyſick, which if they miſs of, or prove ineffectual, they take their flight and leave us, they are not yet immortal but muſt die to be ſo. So theſe Stars that ſhine in our fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, will not always keep above our Horizon, but will at length take time to ſet and diſappear. Theſe men of God are <hi>men,</hi> penetrable by the arrows of the King of terrours, not priviledged nor exempted from the common fate of mortality, neither their more elevated de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of grace, their more exemplary holineſs, nor their continued, though ſtill ripening preparedneſs for heaven, can perpetuate their lives on earth. Their zeal for holineſs, their warmeſt affections, though the flames there kindled riſe never ſo high towards God, will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from colds, thoſe ſmall introductions to all diſtempers: nor the cooleſt of their ſpirits in oppoſition to the heats of paſſion, from burning and malignant Fevers: nor the moſt vigorous activeneſs for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion from the Gout or Palſie, and though their hard hearts are never ſo broken, they may yet meet with the painful agonies of the Stone: nor groans, nor ſighs for ſin, nor prayers, nor praiſes are any Antidotes againſt an infectious Air, though ſometimes preternaturally through the Divine Goodneſs they correct its malignancy. Though our graces are lively, and though our corruptions are mortified, yet we muſt die.</item>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:109618:8"/>
                     <item>2. They have more cauſes of dying than others: they lye more in the road of diſeaſes, dangers and death: their conſtant ſtudies weary their fleſh, and tire their ſpirits out of their bodies: their cares and fears (which powerfully waſt the life) are greater and more conſuming than thoſe of other employments, becauſe terminated upon the ſouls of men, and concerned about Heaven and Hell, everlaſting happineſs and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting miſery. Their anxious cares are that all under their charge may reach the former, and their continuall fears leaſt they fall into the latter. I doubt not but when we come into another world, it will be found that more Miniſters have dyed of their people than of diſeaſes, the unkind and undutifull carriages, the irraclamable lives, and the unchriſtian demeanors of their hearers, of their communicants, theſe are the things that kill and deſtroy them. The ſingle thought that ſome who conſtantly attend their miniſtry are like to be damned, and all their pains and labours utterly loſt upon them, this, this breaks their ſleeps and their hearts too, and ſends them groaning againſt you into another world. Beſides they have ordinarily more enemies than others: upon every lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſtir and diſorder, every fear and jealouſy, every ill news and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment in the ſtate, they are preſently ſought for, haraſſed and ſometimes murdered too. Every ſtorm blows at theſe lights and would ſain extinguiſh them: againſt them are mainly levelled the plots and contrivances of Earth and Hell. The Divel and his agents, his diligent and induſtrious ſubſtitutes cheifly deſiring their ruine. It is no wonder then that they whom all ſtrike at, whom every one wounds and whom every thing conſpires to drive out of this world, at length depart and leave us.</item>
                     <item>3. God in great love calls them away from the miſeries of this world, to ſecure them from the evils to come, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 57.1. He will not always ſuffer his Miniſters to be affronted, his Embaſſadors to be abuſed, nor his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives to be rudely treated, by wicked and impenitent people: but mercifully recall them, and uſually he ſend, in their room ſome ſevere calamity to ſcourge the world: this therefore is no wonder that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts evils upon thoſe who think the death of his Miniſter none, and though it may be eſteemed a fanaticall fancy, yet it is very certain that there is no ſuch ſure prognoſtick of an approaching judgment, as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable mortality of Preachers. Poſſibly God bids them now dye in their beds that they may not hereafter be butchered, and maſſacred by violent &amp; cruel hands: However he gives them a <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> ſends death to ſing <hi>requiems</hi> to their ſouls, &amp; kindly removs them from their cares, their fears, and all their pains &amp; ſtudies to receive the reward of their pious
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109618:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>labours. Miniſters dye, becauſe death is better than life, thereby God fixes an eternall period to all their griefs and ſorrows, and renders them for ever impaſſible. And thus I have done with the doctrinal Part I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed now to the Applicatory. And
<list>
                           <item>1. Learn from hence to bewail the loſs of your <hi>Moſeses,</hi> heartily lament the death of your Miniſters: and be truly troubled (as well you may) at their departure. The days of mourning for Gods <hi>Moſeses</hi> are religiouſly to be obſerved: and not ſpeedily to expend but extend as you feel the want of them: I need uſe no Arguments to work upon your grief at the extinction of the lights of Heaven, you may well cloath your ſouls with blackneſs and ſorrow, when they depart and leave you in the dark. Yet conſider
<list>
                                 <item>1. Who they are, and</item>
                                 <item>2. The time of their deaths, and you will diſſolve into tears of your ſelves.
<list>
                                       <item>1. Who they are, they are Gods Embaſſadours, that treat with you for your fouls: and whoſe buſineſs is to perſwade you to be at peace with him, againſt whom its utterly in vain to war; and to be reconciled to him with whom there is no conteſting. Many private <hi>Iſraelites</hi> might better be ſpared than one <hi>Moſes.</hi> The loſs of a Miniſter is (to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance) the loſs of as many ſouls as might have been converted by him. Mourn therefore that they die, for their deceaſe may be the death of thy ſoul.</item>
                                       <item>2. The time of their death: when they can leaſt be ſpared, and are moſt dearly miſſed. That <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould die at ſuch a time, when the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> were advanced very near the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and juſt entring into their reſt; that he ſhould ſo long lead them, and now leave them, when their hopes and joys were even conſummated, was no doubt of it ſelf, a very fore and pungent addition to their ſorrow: and that our <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould now die juſt at his reſurrection into publick employment ſhould be ſo to ours.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Enquire into your lives whether you have not one way or other, leſs or more procured their removal; and lament and bewail your ſelves as far as you have been the unhappy cauſes of their death, and do this,
<list>
                                 <item>1. You who are more neerly concerned by natural relation to him, who is now gone. It happens but too often that even Miniſters have Domeſtick concauſes of their grief, and conſequently of their ſickneſſes and death: the extravagance of a Wife and the Headineſs of Children are ſomtimes their greateſt and moſt mortal ails: but uſually where rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109618:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>live moſt ſquablingly, when one of them is dead, the remaining, if there be any grace, any good nature, any ſenſe of Religion or morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if the conſcience be not quite ſeared, and the heart incurably hardened, if it be not every jot of it adamant: there will then be ſome relenting remembrances, and ſome penitent reflections upon former miſcarriages. Bear with me, you know I do not uſe to flatter: Are here any that need this advice? if there be, I charge you if you have been guilty of any diſobedience, any undutiful demeanours or of propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any calumniating aſperſions of this deceaſed Miniſter, make haſt to be ſorry, and ſleep in penitential tears, and the more becauſe your refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in one ſenſe is utterly impoſſible, be expeditious and weep hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily for your ſelves, if God perhaps will forgive you.</item>
                                 <item>2. You who are more remotely (and yet neer enough) concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a religious relation, as you have at any time been hearers of this departed Miniſter, take you this advice alſo. Who knows but becauſe you did not return to God, when he laſt preached to you, he is dead, and ſhall preach no more. obſtinate and unreforming hearers are, in too true and too ſad a ſenſe, the murderers of their preachers: they are more affected more afflicted with your ſins than their own diſeaſes. And will you by your iniquities murder the Embaſſadors of Heaven? will nothing ſerve you, nothing ſatiate you but the blood of Miniſters? can you love thoſe your vices that have layd them bleeding at your feet? O mourn, mourn, drench your ſelves with tears and let it be for a perpetual lamentation, not ſo much that your <hi>Moſeſes</hi> die, as that you have killed them. If this doth not call for ſorrow, I know not what doth.</item>
                                 <item>3. <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> As you ever loved Gods Miniſters, as you honour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them, be carefull to imitate (the holineſs of their lives) and practically repeat their Sermons in your heavenly converſations; let them always eccho, and continually reverberate in your ears, praiſe their vertues by your own, and by an unwearied practice of, applaud their Sermons. Was he a good man? the viler wretch art thou, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt ſo bad. Did he preach, did he pray well? the worſe art thou who liveſt ſo ill. Doſt thou commend him? and yet wilt thou ſwear or curſe, or take the name of God in vain? Haſt thou a reſpect for his memory? come, let us ſee it, ſhew it by thy works, what ſin wilt thou leave? what religious duty wilt thou engage in for his ſake? in vain art thou ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh of thy commendations, if thou doſt not leſſen the number of thy ſins. My friends, I am come to ſpeak for, and from him who is in his ſettled ſtate (of happineſs no doubt) who not long ago ſpoke to you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109618:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>from Almighty God; and whom you ſhall never hear again, unleſs at the day of Judgement when he ſhall publickly accuſe thoſe who prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his preaching, but would not live it. And my requeſt from him is that you would ſpeedily repent and return to God, and oh that his death may be a means to convert thoſe that his life and labours miſt to do! Will you do it? or will you not? if you could hear him call you out of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other World, would you deny? and will you becauſe you are treated in a more familiar and leſs ſtartling way? It would be ſome allay to the ſorrows of this day, if the death of this <hi>Moſes</hi> might be ſo far impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as to augment his own joy and the Angels with him in the Regions above by the converſion of ſome Sinners: and our own here, that we may not only weep for ſorrow that he is dead, but weep alſo for joy that by his means the Sinner lives.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Learn from hence to prepare for your own deaths, if God cuts down the fruitful trees, the barren that cumber the ground can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long ſtand. And to keep to the work of this day all the arguments I ſhall uſe to perſwade you to provide for death is, conſider how terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it will be to you if you do not. Death is the King of Terrors, it brings to a terrible God, to a terrible Bar, to a terrible work, it plucks aſunder and divides between the two conſtituent principles of man, draws a ſcreen of darkneſs between him and all the light, the goods, the glories of this world, and fixeth an unmoveable <hi>non ultra</hi> to all his temporal employments, which is very ſad and doleful tidings to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent and unprovided ſinner, who hath no hopes, no happineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the confines of time. That death is terrible moſt that ever paſt into another World are ſerious witneſſes: and who of us all fears not greatly this frightful and impartial leveller, and O that we all did ſo as we ought! that we might not as we ought not, as we would not, as we ſhould not. When thou art ill and weak in body, and far worſe and weaker in thy ſoul: when thy breaths are ſhort and few, and thy vices great and many: thy life een done, and thou not born again, when the Doctor hath given thee up, and the Divine too: when there is no hopes of thy body, and as little of thy ſoul, O how dreadful will the ſight of Millions of unpardoned ſins be, as eaſily and freely as thou now committeſt them? How grievous and burdenſome the remembrance of a Crucified and ſo often rejected Saviour? And how intolerable the thoughts of thoſe Sermons which now thou wretchedly neglecteſt?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109618:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>when thou ſhalt by thy een extinguiſhed light of the Lord within and almoſt out of thee, moſt ſadly ſee all the ſins thou haſt committed, and the mercies thou haſt abuſed in an eager and a cloſe purſuit of thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring ſoul, crying with moſt dreadful and undeniable importunity, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Juſtice, Vengeance, Vengeance: above thee nothing but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciled frowning God, and blackeſt clouds of fluid flaming Brmſtone, een ready to pour upon thee? nothing before thee but an open Hell, its flames furiouſly catching at thy trembling ſoul, where there is no retreating, but as thy breath grows ſhorter, thou ſtill approacheſt nearer: Conſcience violently puſhing thee forward: and on each hand and round about thee, thy weeping friends that now can yield thee no relief at all; and the Divel and his Angels belching out Sulphureous Flames, waiting for Orders to tear thee in pieces, or carry thee away into endleſs miſeries. O the horrors that will then fill thy now uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and careleſs ſoul! O that a man could but ſee into it! what dreadful ſights would there appear? And is it not worth the while to prepare for ſo terrible anenemy as death will be, when cloathed with all theſe dreadfull circumſtances, that he may be thy friend and ſtript of every thing frightfull? Is it not requiſite to make ſome proviſion for ſo ſerious an hour? And to hint a Direction how you ſhould prepare: Be prevailed with to come to Chriſt: I doubt not but all out of Chriſt are bound by all ways they can to make timely proviſion for their great Change: But I cannot think any can be ſufficiently provided to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the King of Terrors, that hath not firſt received the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Lord Jeſus as he is offered in the Goſpel. And to move you towards him: I will onely (remembring death is our preſent ſubject) peremptorily propheſie and preſage to you, that when you come to die you will, you muſt come to Chriſt, to be for ever diſpoſed of by him, and therefore the rather do it now, that he may place you in the manſions of bliſs above. Wilt thou refuſe when the Doctor turns Divine, having drein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy purſe, and to no purpoſe tried all the Apothecaries ſhop; feels thy weak, but haſty pulſe in full ſpeed to death; ſhakes his poſed, his puſled head, and his laſt preſcription is, Take Jeſus Chriſt, make your peace with God, and prepare for another world, put your houſe and your ſoul in order, for you cannot live, and you muſt die, when thy friends take the by thy clammy claiy hand, as cold as are thoſe of great mens ſtatues upon their tombſtones, to take their leaves of thee, and it falls again like a log: when thou haſt done breathing ſhort, and art
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109618:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>fetching a long groan to Eternity, wilt thou then refuſe to come to Chriſt? wilt thou when thou art paſſing to God, thy Spirit is going to him that gave it, when death comes with poſitive and peremptory orders to bring thee to the Judgement ſeat, when forced out of thy bed, ſecured by a guard of Divels, and haled before the inexorable Juſtice to anſwer for all thy miſdemeanours here: when thy ſoul is wreſted out of thy body, God knows very unwilling to part: and cruelly pulled along for all thy weakneſs, for all thy wickedneſs, to the great tribunal of that God, whoſe mercy thou now ſlighteſt, whoſe grace thou rejecteſt, and whoſe tendereſt bowels thou wickedly ſpurn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt againſt, when the news is gone that thou art dead, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains nothing but an empty body: when thy friends anxiouſly feel for breath, and with great fear apply the looking glaſs to ſee a little but can find none: Wilt thou then refuſe to go to Chriſt? If not, O be perſwaded to go now that thou maiſt obtain his pardoning grace and mercy.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Do Gods <hi>Moſeſes</hi> dye, then pray for <hi>Joſhua's</hi> to ſucceed them. Pray that they may fill their rooms, and pray that they may lead you, and that you may cheerfully and conſtantly follow them into the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and to that purpoſe conſcienciouſly take their advice, and obey their command from God, always remembring that your <hi>Joſhua's</hi> will alſo dye, and that you know not how ſoon. Some of you its likely remember an expreſſion of this man of God when he laſt preached here, to this purpoſe. <hi>I Know not whether I may ever preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to you:</hi> ſuch kind of expreſſions do we ſomtimes drop, &amp; you eſteem them malancholy fancies, hut when neither you nor we are aware we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come prophets indeed, and read our own deſtinies. Be it fanaticall or no, I cannot but take notice of the hand of God in your neighbourhood that hath taken away his Miniſters two in one week and left you but one, and when his mouth alſo ſhall be ſtopt with earth and worms, he only that knows all things, knows. O that you would now hear, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as ſure you would, if he who now ſpeaks to you, were to go at this time from this pulpit to his grave and judgment. Well, remember this hereafter, when you are at the funeral of this body: be it ſooner, be it later.</item>
                                 <pb n="16" facs="tcp:109618:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                                 <item>6. The laſt <hi>
                                       <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> If there be any <hi>Joſhua's,</hi> any ſons of the Prophets, pardon me, being it lyes ſo dirctly in my way, if I let fall one applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory word for you with my ſelf. Do Gods <hi>Moſeſes</hi> dye? and are his ancient ſervants ſucceſſively (and indeed by cluſters) dropping and wearing away, ſucceed them then, and may you have their ſucceſs and greater too. <hi>Joſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>N. now therefore ariſe, go over this Jordan,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the wilderness: and by your painfull ardent preaching, &amp; your holy exemplary living conduct the people into the holy land. And to this purpoſe, if I were worthy to adviſe, it ſhould be, that we would take a right level of our reformation, begin it early and high enough, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to our carefull imitation the commands and example of our Bleſſed Saviour, his Apoſtles and the pureſt primitive Churches, without taking any great notice of the uſages and practices of any ſince: and yet bear due regard &amp; a becoming charitable reverence for the whole Chriſtian world, that we would love and honor all, whatever is truly commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all parties but eſpouſe none, that we would profoundly venerate and highly reſpect our ſuperiors, predeceſſors and ſeniors in the Church: but not think ourſelves obliged to be in all things of their opinion, to be their ſeconds, or abettors in all controverſies, ſome of which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps were ingaged in, at leaſt fomented by ſtate or ſecular intereſts: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs far be it from us to ſlight &amp; under value their perſons, or ſcoff and jear at their Sermons, if they ſuit not our palates and do not ſo well accommodate with our juvenile fancies, lets leave that to the <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> of another Church, that we would not meddle with ſtate quarrels &amp; affairs, nor embroyl our ſelves in needleſs Divinity duels; nor (like Church Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retors) run our ſelves into every Eccleſiaſtical ſquabble: that we would endeavour to maintain the ſcriptuaall authority and the rightfull power of paſtors, and yet willingly concede their juſt rights and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the people. That we would cheerfully ſubmit to the church or Magiſtrates prudent determinations of neceſſary circumſtances: and yet carefully ſee what ever pretends to religious decency well proved ſo, before we practiſe. That we would eagerly emulate the gifts and graces of our departed and our dying <hi>Moſeſes;</hi> that we would carefully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of thoſe faults, that ſtatelineſs, confidence, conceitedneſs or what ever els we are apt to blame them for, when we come to their age and circumſtances, and alſo ſtudiouſly labour with deepeſt humility to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, to excell, to outvye them.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. In our Studies.</item>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:109618:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>2. In our Pulpits, and</item>
               <item>3. In our neceſſary Converſes with the world.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. In our Studies. Let us ſtudy peace &amp; love, unity and concord; to find out healing and not dividing principles. Let us make no more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences than indeed there are: and by no means magnifie thoſe that really are, by the glaſſes of prejudice or partiality: but leave them to wrangle about the no or leſſer differences that have nothing elſe to do, and no greater matters to mind. Let us hope for Juſtification upon the ſole account of the merits of the Son of God; and yet (without ſcold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) about <hi>conditions and inſtrumentalities</hi>) aſſert the abſolute and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible neceſſity of holineſs to the beatifical viſion. Let us hold free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and not juſtle out free grace; and our neceſſary concurrence to our own ſalvation, and not depreſs nor depreciate the aſſiſtances of God by advancing too high the natural abilities of man. Let us believe that man can do nothing ſavingly without ſupernatural infuſed grace, and yet that all men can do ſomthing, and are bound (as it is very reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to do all they can. Let us ſit up later, and riſe up earlier, and ſuffer our ſelves to be diverted ſeldomer from our Studies than they.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In our publick approaches to God, let our deportment be grave and reverent, without too much or too little action: let us not move on all four, as if the actions of a Threſher and of a Preacher were to be much alike; and we had been uſed to the former as a preparatory for the latter: nor yet let us be fixed like Statues, leaſt we teach our Auditors to be no more moved than Images. Let us wear and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs in Prayer the loweſt humility, in Preaching the higheſtawfulneſs, and moſt ſerious but unforced Majeſty, and let us do both with that fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor and ardency in our affections, as well as that cleanneſs, maſculineſs in our expreſſions, that men may ſee that we intend their ſouls good and not our own applauſe: not with too formal a ſetneſs, an over fineſs of words and Rhetorick, like thoſe who all week long anxiouſly hunt after Plays and Romances, wherewith to treat their hearers on the Sabbath, as if they deſigned the tickling of their fancies and the gratifying their curioſities, and not the reforming of their lives, and the ſaving of their ſouls: nor yet to make work for jearing <hi>debate-makers.</hi> Hereafter cloath the great things of God with rude and clowniſh ſpeech, like thoſe that Santer up and down, that Chat and Coffe-houſe away their time, and then entertain their Auditors with their ſudden effuſions and idle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109618:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>impertinences, ſlovenly metaphors and numberleſs tautologies, as if to invoke God, and repreſent him were the eaſieſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince in the world. Let us remember both to enflame the affections and lighten the underſtanding, and not belabour the one with out regarding the other, let us offer the promiſes, and fire the theatningst to draw or to drive men from their ſins, not valueing their jears who ſcoff at the preaching of grace; nor their cenſure of <hi>legal preachers</hi> who fancy Chriſt menaces no part of his Goſpel. In a word let us in this (as in all things) make the Apoſtles our Preſidents, ſince it is very likely their way of preaching will do moſt good.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In our needfull converſes with this world, let us make it appear we are of another: and in providing the neceſſaries of our pilgrimage that <hi>we ſeek another country.</hi> When employed about the urgent buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (the little <hi>other things</hi> of our ſelves as men) let us firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God; <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. and not looſe our ſelves and forget our ſpiritual concerns by too long parentheſes in our ſecular. Let our flames of love, our beams of knowledge ſo burn, ſo ſhine as theirs ſhould, who are the burning ſhining light, of the world, that <hi>others may find by us the way to happineſs, that they may ſee our good works and glorifie our father which is in Heaven. Mat.</hi> 5.16. Let there be no diſcord, but the ſweeteſt harmony between our inſtructions and our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations.</p>
            <p>Let us not forget what we ſpoke for God, when we come to deal with men, like thoſe (I hope otherwiſe) good Miniſters, who will make a heavy ado about love and unity in the pulpit, and then look ſhy upon one another when they come down: and talk loudly againſt diviſions and animoſiities amongſt different perſwaſions and yet deny communion to any but thoſe of their own: that in their prayers confeſs they are very ſorry for the diſtances amongſt good people of divers judgments, and yet will not give the Lords ſupper to any that are not of their own ſiſe, and that come not full up to themſelves. Away Hyprocriſies! Let us (my brethren) do that which hath been long vainly talked of: let us (whether our opinions jump or no) love, converſe and communicate together. <hi>Be we ſtrong and of good Courage; be we not afraid, nor at all diſmayed, Joſh.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Come what can come between this and Heaven. Obſerve we carefully the laws of God, turn we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the right hand</hi> of Popery, Will Worſhip, and Idolotry, <hi>nor to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109618:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>left</hi> of Hereſy, Error and Anarchy: run we not to the Church of <hi>Rome nor any ſuperſtitious one</hi> for fear of Schiſm, nor <hi>into no Churches.</hi> to avoid Superſtition and formality. <hi>Meditate we upon the word of God day and night v.</hi> 8. and do we accordingly, <hi>ſo ſhall we proſper where-ever we go, ſo ſhall we have good ſucceſs, and ſo will the Lord be with us as be was with</hi> Moſes. <hi>He will not fail us, nor forſake us,</hi> Joſhua 1.5.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat thou mayſt not wrong either thy ſelf or the Authour, be perſwaded before thou readeſt to correct, as thou art here inſtructed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 2 lin. 17. r.</hi> Monios. <hi>l. 18. r.</hi> be. <hi>l. 24. dele</hi> a. <hi>p. 3. l. 20. r.</hi> force or compulſion. <hi>l. 36. r.</hi> velliety, <hi>p. 7. l. 21. r.</hi> words. <hi>p. 8. l. 31. r.</hi> whirls. <hi>p. 9. l. 17 r.</hi> eaſily. <hi>l. 20. r.</hi> or they prove. <hi>l. 21.</hi> blot ſo before theſe. <hi>l. 31. r.</hi> coolneſs. <hi>32. r.</hi> nor their. <hi>p. 11. l. 8. r.</hi> expire not expend. <hi>p. 12. l. 10. r.</hi> ſteep not ſleep. Some other leſſor errors there are which thy own diſcretion will correct without giving thee any further trouble here.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109618:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
